Okay, good morning. Today is שבת כ"ז, Shabbos Kof Zayin, and we
actually pick up on כ"ז, Kof Zayin,
and we are אמר רבא, Amar Rava, one, two, three, five lines
from the top left, two words into the line. We had finally,
as I mentioned, like good 25, 26 בלאט blatt into the מסכת,
masechet, are now talking about the language one uses when one does
תמורה. temurah. Let's again remind ourselves that it is a sin to
do תמורה, temurah, and that the, and that it is a language
of, the language of exchange, תחת, tachat, תמורה, temurah, חליפה, chalifa, is
an act of תמורה. temurah. If it is a language of to
be מחלל, mechallel, to desanctify the object and to transfer it then
to another one, then that is not a language of תמורה. temurah.
And if the original animal is a בעל מום, ba'al mum, then
actually that's what you're supposed to do. And if it's not a
בעל מום, ba'al mum, then at least you didn't do anything. So,
and we had emphasized that the difference is, which are you starting
from? If you're starting from the sanctified animal and you focus on
removing its status, that's good. If you start with, if you leave
the sanctified animal where it is and you start with the unsanctified
one, the חולין, chullin, and you try to have it take the
place of the sanctified one, then you are, you know, undercutting, you
are, you are impinging on the status of the sanctified one. That
is an act of תמורה. temurah. It's also what the גמרא Gemara
calls אתפוסא, atfusa, you're grabbing. The sanctity of the first one is
still in its place, it's being grabbed onto the other one and
the קדושה kedusha is transferred. And now what the גמרא Gemara has
just said is that the word תחת, tachat, instead of, can have
a sense of staying in your place, תחתיה, tachtah, you know, אם
תחתיה, im tachtah, or could have a sense which would be the
language of תמורה, temurah, the first one stays in its place, or
could have a language of exchange and it depends on context. By
קדשי בדק הבית kodshei bedek habayis where you don't have a sense
of תמורה, temurah, it means exchange, excuse me, not exchange, transfer, I
should say, transfer, whereas when you have, and by קדשי קרבנות kodshei
korbanot where you have a concept of תמורה, temurah, it has a
sense of the first one staying in its place and attempt to
replace, maybe that's a better word than exchange, replace, and therefore that
is a תמורה temurah language. But the problem still is, and this
is what the גמרא Gemara is going to turn itself to, the
problem still is why would I want to interpret it as תמורה
temurah if that's an עבירה? aveira? So now let's take a look
at even if it's a meaningful interpretation. So let's take a look
now what אמר רבא Amar Rava says. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so
says רבא, Rava, five lines down, כ"ז עמוד א', Kof Zayin Amud
Aleph, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, אפילו בקדשי מזבח, afilu bekodshei mizbe'ach, even
if when you're dealing with קרבנות, korbanot, משתכח ללישנא דחולי, mishtachas lelishna
dechulei, you
we can find the language of תחת tachat to mean to desanctify,
to be מחלל, mechallel, to redeem, to desanctify, not to replace. How,
what would that be case be? כגון דהוה הקדש בעל מום, kegon
dehayah hekdesh ba'al mum, for example, if the קרבן korban had a
מום mum and it was supposed to be redeemed. So any place
where redeeming is a meaningful concept, okay, we will take this ambiguous
word תחת tachat and choose to interpret it in the way it
should be used. So since in this context, either you're dealing with
בדק הבית, bedek habayis, temple treasury, or a קרבן korban with a
מום, mum, what are you supposed to do? You're supposed to redeem
it. So you have this ambiguous phrase תחת, tachat, but if you're
supposed to redeem it, we're going to read that as redeeming. That's
what you're supposed to do since that's what the word can mean.
Only if it's not possible to redeem and you're using the word
תחת, tachat, will we give it the worst interpretation, the one of
תמורה, temurah, because at least that somehow is an act that is
done. You know, it's funny again, why don't we just interpret it
in a way that you didn't sin? But apparently the argument there
is, well, if we interpret it to be redeem and the animal
was unblemished and a קרבן, korban, then you said garbage, you said
meaningless words, redemption is not a meaningful concept. If, however, you said
the word meant תמורה, temurah, at least it was meaningful. It was
bad, but it was meaningful, and therefore you did the sin and
the other object gets the קדושה. kedusha. So the הלכה halacha is
we'll interpret it in a way that is meaningful rather than meaningless,
even if the consequence is that you've done a תמורה. temurah. But
if it's a קרבן korban with a מום, mum, then a meaningful
interpretation is redemption and that's how we will interpret it. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara goes on. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi,
אפילו בבעל מום נמי משתכח ללישנא דחולי, afilu beba'al mum nami mishtachas
lelishna dechulei, not so fast. Even if the animal had a blemish,
we might interpret it, A, you're right, sometimes we'll interpret it as
אחולי, achulei, redemption, desanctifying, but also there are times where we might
interpret it as תמורה, temurah, the bad language, ומשתכח ללישנא דאתפוסא, umishtachas
lelishna de'atfusa, to grab hold of. What is the example? And here
context makes all the difference. And this is probably the clearest גמרא
Gemara that clarifies the conceptual difference between redemption, desanctifying on the one
hand, and תמורה, temurah, exchange or replacing on the other. ידו אקדש,
Yadah a-kodesh, if your hand is on the sanctified animal, the קרבן
korban with a מום, mum, and then you say תחת, tachat, חולו,
chulu, you have desanctified it, meaning it's a, you interpret it as
a language of redemption, because what is the language of redemption? To
remove the קדושה, kedusha, to start with the holy object, to start
with the sacrifice. So if your hand is on the sacrifice and
you say this ambiguous phrase, we'll interpret it in the most meaningful
way, in this context the meaningful way
is אחולי, achulei, redeem.
No, presumably if it were not a בעל מום baal mum the
language is not meaningful then we're going to interpret it still the
only way that it's meaningful. We bias towards the meaningful interpretation. But
if you can go in either way, right, with an animal with
a מום mum it could either a meaningful interpretation is either תמורה
temurah or redemption. So when both things are options we will use
the context of where your hand is on.
Okay, I'll interpret it favorably to you in that way.
Meaning, right, interpret in the best way, תמורה. temurah. Exactly. Exactly. Okay.
So I'll go back and I'll sum that up, that's correct. Okay,
ידו הקודש חול הוי. yado hakodesh chol havei. ידו החול yado hachol
if however your hand is on the non-sanctified one, so then you
are defining your act as taking the non-sanctified one and having it
replace the sanctified. That's not an act of redemption. That's an act
of exchange or replacement. In that case, קודש הוי kodesh havei even
if the sanctified one has a מום, mum, the sanctified one retains
its sanctity and the de-sanctified one becomes sanctified because that's what's a
result of תמורה. temurah. So this is a great illustration of the
conceptual difference between תמורה temurah and פדיון pidyon or לחלל. lechallel. תמורה
temurah is you keep the sanctified one where it is, you take
the unsanctified one and you try to have it take the place
of the sanctified. You're undercutting as it were, you know, you're trying
to dethrone the sanctified one. That's the problematic act and because the
sanctified one has its sanctity, it grabs onto the de-sanctified. So that's
when you start with the חול. chol. When you start with the
קודש, kodesh, you are fundamentally removing the sanctity. That is acceptable if
it has a מום. mum. So what does what is the consequence?
Well, if you use a language that is unambiguous, חריפין, charifin, תמורה
temurah on the one hand or מחולל mechulal on the other hand,
unambiguous language, we don't care about your context. Your language is very
clear what it means. If you use the only case where context
matters is an ambiguous phrase תחת. tachat. As Michael pointed out with
his question, even there we will disregard context to give it a
meaningful interpretation rather than a meaningless interpretation. So we won't be able
to interpret it as redeem if the animal doesn't have a blemish.
That is a meaningless interpretation of that word. So we will always
we will always choose the meaningful interpretation over the meaningless one. However,
if you have two possible meaningful interpretations, the animal has a מום,
mum, it could either mean redeem or mean תמורה. temurah. So the
word is ambiguous and there could be two meaningful interpretations. There we
will use the context to explain based on where your hand is
on, how you're showing what you are doing.
If he redeems the animal the money goes to the treasury.
If he redeems the animal, if it's a קרבן korban then the
other animal becomes a קרבן. korban. He redeems it onto another animal,
that becomes the קרבן. korban. If it is a sanctified for the
treasury and he redeems it, then the money goes to the treasury.
Yes. Okay.
If his hand is on both of them?
Well, then we're back to square one where we said, you know,
if you have two meaningful interpretations, you know, it's like the issue
before. So where if it were a בעל מום baal mum and
it's a meaningful interpretation, we would rather give it the better interpretation
rather than the worse one. Okay. If it's not a בעל מום
baal mum then we'll give it the meaningful interpretation which is תמורה
temurah even though it's not a favorable one.
When you bring these two cows or whatever it is to a
כהן kohen and they decide or do you decide?
No, no, you're doing this yourself.
But how can you trust?
Why can't you? You sanctify things and you can transfer the קדושה.
kedusha. Now it is true that if you sanctify something to the
temple treasury, once you give it over to the temple, the temple
can transfer the קדושה. kedusha. But we could be and I'll talk
about that a little later today, but once it's still in your
possession you could transfer the קדושה kedusha to something else and give
the other thing. That's you have that right to transfer the קדושה
kedusha assuming it is either a קרבן korban with a מום mum
or it is something given over to the temple treasury. You are
able to do that. When by the way you transfer the קדושה
kedusha you have to add a חומש chomesh if you're the owner
that adds it. Right. Okay. Yes. And the גמרא Gemara says that
we trust
we trust that person.
Yeah, exactly. As with a lot of things, we say we trust
him to tell us that he sanctified it. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara goes on. So anyway this is a great גמרא Gemara
that speaks to the conceptual difference between מחלל mechallel and תמורה temurah
and tells us sort of when we go, you know, our first
we go by the meaning of the words, if there's ambiguity we
go by what's meaningful, and if that still does not determine we
go by the context. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says, בעי אביי,
baei Abaye, אביי Abaye asks, היו לפניו שתי בהמות של קודש בעלות
מום ושתי בהמות של חול תמימות. hayu lefanav shtei behemot shel kodesh
baalot mum ushtei behemot shel chol temimot. You had in front of
you two animals that had a blemish and two animals that were
unblemished. Now this first case really could be one animal on each
side. The reason we're saying two and two is we're about to
go into other cases that are more complex that are based on
two on each side, but this one could have been simplified as
one on each side. So you have anyway unblemished and blemished, excuse
me, right, and the sanctified ones have a blemish. So when the
sanctified ones have a blemish. So when the sanctified ones have a
blemish. Remember there are possibly two meaningful interpretations when you're going to
use the word תחת. tachas. It could mean redeem, it could mean
תמורה. temurah. There are two possible interpretations. We just said in that
case, right, it depends where your hand is on. Now it's going
to ask Michael's question essentially. That's if your hand is on both,
or your hand is on neither. So what's the הלכה? halacha? ואמר
הרי אלו תחת אלו. V'amar harei elu tachas elu. So here you
go. You said תחת, tachas, your hand wasn't on either, okay, either
interpretation was meaningful. מהו? Mahu? What are we going to say? מי
אמרינן לאתפוסינהו בלקי? Mi amrinan l'atfusinhu b'laki?
Do we say that it means to grab hold of, meaning to
try to replace and exchange, the תמורה temurah language and you get
lashes? או דילמא כל היכא דאיכא היתירא לא שביק איניש היתירא ועביד
איסורא? O dilma kol heicha d'ika heiteira lo shavik inish heiteira v'avid
issura? Or do we say that as long as you can do
it in a permissible way, you're not going to abandon a permissible
way and do a forbidden one? Now that's a phrase that normally
means like, you know, sort of makes us question your motivation. Do
we assume if you had kosher meat and treif meat in front
of you, you would have left the kosher to eat the treif,
assuming that they were all other things were equal? But here really
it might not be a question and the הגה Gra takes out
this phrase. It might not be a question of motivation. Here really
the issue is like how are we going to choose to interpret
your words? Maybe we should bias towards an interpretation if both interpretations
are meaningful, let us have a bias towards a favorable interpretation rather
than an unfavorable interpretation. Okay, and that's of course what the גמרא
Gemara concludes and I would say that was pretty implicit in רבא's
Rava initial statement, right?
Thanks. ואי פנצלו לומר V'ee pintzlu lomar if you want to say
כל
היכא דאיכא היתירא לא שביק איניש ועביד איסורא, kol heicha d'ika heiteira
lo shavik inish v'avid issura, that if there is a positive interpretation
we would opt for a positive one. Right, so that's basically what
we've been assuming now. תחת Tachas is ambiguous. We will interpret it,
if there's only one meaningful way to interpret it we'll interpret it
the one meaningful way. If there's two meaningful, even if that's to
your detriment, if there's two meaningful ways to interpret, says אביי Abaye
now, I would say it was probably implicit in רבא, Rava, we
will interpret it in the more favorable way. If there is however,
if there is context, then we will go by the context based
on where your hands are. So suffice fine, I get it, I
get that, two equal interpretations both meaningful, we'll choose the more favorable
one. Here's my next question. היו לפניו, Hayu lefanav, and this really
what was leading up to, היו לפניו שתי בהמות של קודש, hayu
lefanav shtei beheimot shel kodesh, and here you see why we're dealing
with two. You had two animals that were sacrifices, sanctified as sacrifices.
ואחת מהן בעלת מום, V'achat meihen ba'alat mum, and you had one
of them was a blemish. So with the one with the blemish,
a possible positive interpretation is possible, redemption. The unblemished one is only
a negative interpretation, תמורה, temurah, right? Okay, so now you with these
two animals if you're going to use the word תחת, tachas, you
got the scenario in your head? If you're going to use the
word תחת, tachas, it's with the unblemished one it has to mean
תמורה. temurah. With the blemished one it could have a positive meaning
which means redemption. ושתי בהמות
של חולין, V'shtei beheimot shel chullin, and you have two animals of
חולין chullin in front of you. ואחת מהן בעלת מום, V'achat meihen
ba'alat mum, and one of them has a blemish. So again you
have one animal, one blemished, one unblemished of קרבן, korban, one blemished,
one unblemished of חולין. chullin. We're on the first wide line of
חזן עמוד א. chazan amud aleph. ואמר הרי אלו תחת אלו, V'amar
harei elu tachas elu, these are תחת tachas those. You use the
word תחת, tachas, this ambiguous word, for two against two, blemished and
unblemished on each side. Okay, מהו? Mahu? How are we going to
choose to interpret the words? Now we'll read our גרסא girsa then
I'll tell you the הגה Gra completely reverses the order. Okay, but
anyway here's our גרסא. girsa. מי אמרינן תמימה תחת תמימה? Mi amrinan
tmimah tachas tmimah? Should we assume that what you meant was to
match up the likes? So you have blemished and unblemished קרבן korban
here, blemished and unblemished חולין chullin here. The word תחת tachas as
we've been discussing has an ambiguous term. It could mean to redeem
which is good when you're dealing with a בעל מום, ba'al mum,
it could mean תמורה temurah which obviously has negative consequences. So you're
going to say these two, these two תחת tachas these two. Okay,
what how are we going to interpret it? Should we line up
the likes, תמים tamim for תמים, tamim, בעל מום ba'al mum for
בעל מום? ba'al mum? And then what would be the consequence of
that's what you meant? So let's take a look. תמימה תחת תמימה
לאתפוסי. Tmimah tachas tmimah l'atfusi. Now when you're dealing with an unblemished,
the only thing your words can mean is תמורה, temurah, is the
bad thing. So clearly when you're going to be dealing with the
unblemished one here, the תמים tamim one here, your words have to
mean תמורה temurah and you at least will get lashes for that
and the other thing will become קדוש. kadosh. That's clear, that's unquestioned.
But now we're going to say בעלת מום תחת בעלת מום, ba'alat
mum tachas ba'alat mum, you're lining up the בעל מום, ba'al mum,
so that at least is לחולין, l'chullin, that at least means to
redeem. Okay, so since it redeems at least for the בעל מום
ba'al mum you won't get lashes. Okay, that makes sense. What's the
alternative? או דילמא, O dilma, or do we say תמימה דחולין תחת
בעלת מום דהקדש, tmimah d'chullin tachas ba'alat mum d'hekdesh, בעלת מום דחולין
תחת תמימה דהקדש, ba'alat mum d'chullin tachas tmimah d'hekdesh, you're crossing over.
So the unblemished one here of קרבן korban you're trying to do
on the בעל מום. ba'al mum. Fine, that's still תמורה. temurah. When
you start with an unblemished קרבן, korban, the language of תחת tachas
can only mean תמורה. temurah. That's never changed. Now you start with
the blemished one here and unblemished one here. So now we're going
to say that that means somehow instead of meaning redemption, that means
תמורה. temurah. Why should it mean... Why should it mean תמורה tmurah
in that case? If anything, that more should mean redemption. You're taking
from the unblemished, I'm sorry, you're taking from the
unblemished, transferring it to the ble-, no, you're taking from the blemished,
transferring it to the unblemished. That's exactly what you're supposed to do.
That should be redemption. But the גמרא Gemara here, at least the
language we have, one minute, says בעל מום דחולין ba'al mum dechullin
excuse me, בעל מום דהקדש ba'al mum dehekdesh תמימה דחולין תחת בעל
מום דהקדש, tmimah dechullin tachat ba'al mum dehekdesh, בעל מום דחולין תחת
תמימה דהקדש, ba'al mum dechullin tachat tmimah dehekdesh, ובתרוייהו לקי. uvetravaihu laki.
You get lashes for both. So again, this question is hard to
understand because you again, when you start with the unblemished one of
הקדש, hekdesh, your תחת tachat can only mean תמורה tmurah because redemption
is not a concept and you get lashes. When you start with
the blemished, if anything, the blemished to unblemished is exactly the act
of פדיון. pidyon. Why should we translate it that way and get
and getting lashes? So, but if that's true, then even when blemished
blemished. So Michael says, oh, well the reason we're going to translate
this as תמורה tmurah is because we translated this one as תמורה.
tmurah. Okay, but that's true even if you line it up תמים
תמים בעל מום בעל מום, tamim tamim ba'al mum ba'al mum, right?
So if your argument is because this means תמורה, tmurah, that one
should mean תמורה, tmurah, it should be true regardless of how the
match up is.
So why would you redeem a blemished for a blemished?
There's no good reason. So I'll get back to that in a
minute. So רש"י Rashi says is, you're right. רש"י Rashi basically says
because the תמים tamim one it has to mean תמורה, tmurah, by
the blemished one it means תמורה. tmurah. So if that's true, why
when it's blemished against blemished is it not a problem? So רש"י
Rashi says a radical thing. רש"י Rashi says the תורה Torah says
by תמורה tmurah רע בטוב או טוב ברע. ra betov o tov
bera. If it's רע ברע, ra bera, if it's a מום mum
and a מום, mum, that's not an act of תמורה. tmurah. And
since that can't be an act of תמורה, tmurah, we're forced to
interpret that as redemption. So our inclination is to translate everything as
תמורה tmurah because this one is תמורה, tmurah, but רע ברע ra
bera can't be that and therefore it that allows that to be
a translated as redemption. That's the way רש"י Rashi says. תוספות Tosafot
goes a little crazy because תוספות Tosafot says maybe this is completely
wrong, we have never heard that רע ברע ra bera is not
תמורה tmurah and if anything the גמרא Gemara before made it clear
that it was תמורה. tmurah. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot does not like
that at all. And but because there's a real question here why
the גמרא Gemara is assuming that, you know, בעל מום ba'al mum
for תמים tamim is תמורה tmurah more than the other case, the
גר"א Gra completely reverses the גירסא. girsa. And the גר"א Gra says
when it's בעל מום ba'al mum for בעל מום, ba'al mum, like
James said, בעל מום ba'al mum for בעל מום, ba'al mum, there's
no reason to do that. So that's we're not going to translate
that as redemption, we're going to have that follow the תמים. tamim.
If the תמים tamim means תמורה, tmurah, that means תמורה. tmurah. That's
a mean why would you redeem a בעל מום ba'al mum on
a בעל מום? ba'al mum? It'll be determined by the first one
which clearly means תמורה. tmurah. But if it's a בעל מום ba'al
mum and a תמים, tamim, then that's the classic act of redemption.
So we'll allow the first one to mean תמורה tmurah and the
second one to mean redemption. So that's why the גר"א Gra completely
flips the גירסא. girsa. But רש"י Rashi who has it his way
has to come up with this very new idea that a בעל
מום ba'al mum for a בעל מום ba'al mum is not an
act of a תמורה. tmurah. Okay, so now let's keep on going.
What's next?
I mean he tried to do
פדיון, pidyon, right? Yeah, but it doesn't work or it does work.
What? Meaning if I try to be פודה podeh a בעל מום
ba'al mum on another בעל מום. ba'al mum. Oh, it totally works.
Sure, you could be פודה podeh a בעל מום ba'al mum on
תמימים. tmimim. I could be פודה podeh a בעל מום ba'al mum
on my car. It's just that eventually it has to transfer to
an actual animal or money.
Okay, so the second one is the unsanctified, whatever it is, unsanctified,
but I still have to do another פדיון pidyon on the one
that I just did. Sure, but there's no it's not like an
עבירה aveirah to do that.
Right. It's like transferring it onto money. Right.
No, no, money works though.
I mean you're saying is it like being מקדיש makdish a בעל
מום ba'al mum as a קרבן? korban? Probably not, no, because it's
still ultimately to it's now קדושת דמים. kedushat damim. I don't think
that that would be that.
I don't feel like a fifth to it though.
No, you would actually, but that's a different הלכה. halacha. All right,
let's keep on going. So that's okay, so that's the two against
two which is right, a little bit unclear on, you know, there
are two interpretations why, but the basic point is by the תמים
tamim it has to mean תמורה. tmurah. How are we going to
interpret, especially if you didn't even say two sentences, it was one
sentence, two against two, and for one of the options it meant
תמורה, tmurah, can we interpret it for the other animal in a
more positive light as פדיון pidyon redemption? Now we go on with
another scenario.
ואם תמצי לומר ve'im timtzi lomar כל היכא דאיכא היתירא לא עבדי
איסורא kol heicha de'ika heiteira lo avdi issura ולחולי הוא דלא לקי
velachullin hu delo laki and that whenever there's a היתר heter you
don't do an איסור issur which really wouldn't is not just as
I said, not really a question of motivation as much as how
we're going to choose to interpret. If it is possible to interpret
it in a meaningful way in a more positive light, we won't
interpret it as a negative way in a more detrimental way. So
even though by the תמים tamim it has to mean תמורה tmurah
because that's the only meaningful interpretation, by the בעל מום, ba'al mum,
even though it was the exact same sentence, we'll interpret that word
to mean redemption. Okay, so we're always going to choose the more
positive interpretation. Fine. But let me ask another question. היו לפניו שלש
בהמות של קודש hayu lefanav shalosh behemot shel kodesh ואחת מהן בעלת
מום. ve'achat mehen ba'alat mum. Let's say you had three that were
קודש, kodesh, two were תמים tamim and one was a בעל מום.
ba'al mum. So now the two that are תמים tamim when you
say the word תחת, tachat, it can only mean תמורה. tmurah. You
cannot say a
lot, it was one sentence, two against two. So now two-thirds of
the group, it means תמורה, temurah, right? So will the fact that
the majority of the group it means תמורה temurah determine what that
word means even for the one-third of the group? Okay, so you
have three of them שכלן תמימות, shekulan temimot, I'm sorry, של קדש
shel kodesh ואחת מהן בעלת מום ve'achat mehem ba'alat mum and opposite
it you have three unblemished animals that are חולין chulin and one
says הרי אלו תחת אלו, harei elu tachat elu, these are in
exchange for those, one phrase for the whole group, one phrase of
תחת. tachat. There do we say that even though normally we'll interpret
positively, at least here majority should
determine? מי אמרינן מדמימות תחת תמימות לאתפוסי Mi amrinan midemimot tachat temimot
le'atpusei since by the unblemished the only thing the word תחת tachat
can mean is תמורה temurah and it grabs hold, not redeeming, תמימות
נמי תחת בעל מום לאתפוסי temimot nami tachat ba'al mum le'atpusei so
if two-thirds of the group that's what the word means, it's got
to mean it even for the third animal of the group, for
the בעל מום. ba'al mum. או דילמא O dilma or do we
say no, even in this case we will insist on a favorable
interpretation when possible. הכא נמי כל היכא דאיכא היתירא לא עביד איסורא
Hacha nami kol heicha de'ika heiteira lo avid issura whenever there's היתר
heter you will not do an איסור, issur, we won't interpret it
as an
איסור, issur, והיא בתרייתא לחולין הוי vehi batraita lechulin havei means redemption.
ואי תימא לומר הכא נמי כיון דאיכא גברא לא אתחזק באיסורא Ve'im
tima lomar hacha nami keivan de'ika gavra lo itchazek be'issura ah maybe
here we'll interpret favorably because you have not sort of created a
חזקה, chazakah, you have not established a pattern that you do acts
of תמורה temurah because you've only done it twice with two of
the animals. A חזקה chazakah requires three times. So therefore because you
haven't established a pattern, we're still prepared to interpret your words favorably.
Again, or we assume that it was your intention, motivation. This phrase
could be a question of what we're guessing your intention is or
what we're choosing to interpret as. Anyway, we'll say that as long
as you haven't established a pattern, לא שביק היתירא ועביד איסורא lo
shevik heiteira ve'avid issura you're not doing an איסור. issur. Let me
just ask a... well, that is a good question.
Maybe he says I don't know what I was thinking, I just
said תחת. tachat. Okay, but that's a good question in general, you're
right. By הקדש hekdesh how much do we ask? It's also an
interesting question that even though by הקדש hekdesh normally we say that
הפלאה hafla'ah your דעת da'at matters, okay, we say דברים שבלב אינם
דברים devarim shebelev einam devarim by עסק הקדשה, esek hekdashah, by תמורה
temurah if you remember there was a whole סוגיא sugya that לבו
ושגגתו כאחד. libo veshigagato ke'echad. So it could be by תמורה temurah
since you get lashes, it's more of an external act and therefore
we don't... you're not as prepared to go by what you say
your intention was.
Would we even ask you if we could?
It's a little bit unclear, possibly not. I mean the whole גמרא
Gemara before, it's true there was גמרא Gemara before וכך נתכוונתי מתחילה
vechach nitkavanti mitechilah and so on, but you know, but again, it's
a little bit of a question how much we go by asking
you when it comes to a question of תמורה temurah as opposed
to a question of הקדשה. hekdashah.
Do we say תמורה temurah needs a warning?
Yes, the גמרא Gemara before said it was a
לאו שאין בו מעשה. lav she'ein bo ma'aseh.
התראה hatra'ah I suppose it depends on what your approach is to
the earlier גמרא Gemara about לבו ושגגתו כאחד. libo veshigagato ke'echad. If
you say לבו ושגגתו כאחד libo veshigagato ke'echad really means even for
מלקות malkut which was a whole debate of that earlier גמרא, Gemara,
then it might not need warning. Okay, הכא נמי hacha nami anyway
should we say here... okay, so therefore we say as long as
you haven't established a
pattern, לא שביק היתירא ועביד איסורא. lo shevik heiteira ve'avid issura. So
if that's true, then בעי רב אשי. ba'ei Rav Ashi. Based on
that, Rav Ashi asks the following question: היו לפניו ארבע בהמות של
קדש Hayu lefano arba behemot shel kodesh now we have four ואחת
מהן בעלת מום ve'achat mehem ba'alat mum one is a בעל מום
ba'al mum וארבע בהמות של חולין ve'arba behemot shel chulin ואמר הרי
אלו תחת אלו ve'amar harei elu tachat elu these are exchanged for
those. So for the first three that are unblemished, the only thing
the word תחת tachat can mean is תמורה. temurah. Now you've done
the חטא chet three times. You've done it three times. I know,
it's interesting. Right, that's the idea of establishing a חזקה. chazakah. You
might think in one act it's not establishing a חזקה chazakah on
three times. It is for... I know, I know. There's a great
רמב"ם. Rambam. The רמב"ם Rambam in general has an interesting approach towards
ethical behavior and sort of running through also in his הקדמה לפרקי
אבות hakdamah lePirkei Avot in שמונה פרקים Shemonah Perakim and running through
his whole interpretation of פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot, he emphasizes that the
purpose of a lot of these sort of ethical acts are not
necessarily because the good it does for the other person, but because
of how it develops your moral character. And on the basis of
that, he interprets the line in פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot that says
הכל לפי המעשה ולא לפי רוב המעשה. hakol lefi hama'aseh velo lefi
rov hama'aseh. It's all goes by the action, not by the size
of the action, or something like that. So what does that mean?
The רמב"ם Rambam says this means that it's better to give צדקה
tzedakah a thousand times of a dollar each time than to give
one time a thousand dollars. Because if you give a dollar each
time, it more, you know, reinforces into your character the sense that
you give צדקה tzedakah and that you are and that that's the
type of character that you have. So I agree with you, the
idea of אתחזק באיסורא, itchazek be'issura, you'd think it would have to
be three separate acts, not one bigger act of three things. Anyways,
that's the גמרא's Gemara question. Do we say in that case מהו?
mahu? What do we say there?
הכא ודאי כיון דאתחזק גברא באיסורא לקי בארבע מלקיות. Hacha vadai keivan
de'itchazek gavra be'issura laki be'arba malkiyot. Do we
say... That's either what we're going to assume your motivation is or
what I would more say is that's how we're going to choose
to interpret your words, right? By the way, in terms of התראת
ספק, hasra'at safek, since it's all one act, you could say it's
an interesting question. In a way, there's an element of התראת ספק
hasra'at safek here, right? Because we don't know how to interpret your
words, but you could sort of say, "Don't do this act. If
you do this act, you'll get lashes." So maybe you don't have
to say how many lashes you'll get in terms of since you
do one act. So that's an interesting question, right? Would you have
to say you'll get three sets of lashes, you'll get four sets
of lashes? So anyway, the גמרא Gemara presumably assumes you could get
lashes without yet knowing, you know, at the time.
Unless there's a warning that kind of informs you.
Oh, that's also true. Based on the warning, it will define what
you're doing. או דילמא, O dilma, what do we say? אף על
גב דאתחזק באיסורא, Af al gav de'itchazek be'issura, even when you've established
that pattern, לא שבקי איניש דעביד איסורא, lo shavke inish de'avid issura,
we're not going to either... we'll either assume that wasn't your motivation
or we're not... we won't interpret it in that light. והוי בתרייתא
אחולי, Ve'havi batrayta achulei, and even the last one means redemption. והוי,
Ve'havi, and the גמרא Gemara of course ends with תיקו. teiku. Okay,
as we were expecting, that's how it was going to be the
end. Those are fascinating thought questions. And again, what is really great
here is you see, A, conceptually the difference between תמורה temurah and
פדיון. pidyon. פדיון pidyon is starting with the קודש, kodesh, removing the
קדושה. kedusha. תמורה temurah is trying to replace. That's where it is,
and you're taking this other thing and you're trying to dethrone the
קודש kodesh one. Because of that, that's why it's a forbidden act
and that's also why it becomes קדוש kadosh because the other one
has retained its status in that act. And when your language is
unambiguous, תמורה temurah on the one hand, פדיון pidyon on the other,
אחולי achulei on the other, then of course we go by your
language. If your language is ambiguous, תחת, tachas, which gives the גמרא
Gemara the opportunity to raise all these fascinating questions, how do we
interpret an ambiguous language? So the first point is, is we'll interpret
it in a meaningful way rather than in a meaningless way, even
if it's to your detriment. So if the animal is a תמים,
tamim, then the language of פדיון pidyon is meaningless. The language of
תמורה, temurah, well that is a meaningful language, and therefore that's how
we'll interpret it if you start with an animal that is... that
is תמים. tamim. If, however, you start with a בעל מום, ba'al
mum, then both mean... then both interpretations are possible. And therefore we
will be... there are two meaningful interpretations. We will bias ourselves towards
a more favorable interpretation. Those were all these examples, maybe even if
there's a lot of reason to say otherwise, we'll bias ourselves towards
a favorable interpretation, even if it was all done in one phrase.
But what... what the גמרא Gemara said before, that... that I think
you missed when you came a little late, but I'll repeat it
because it's so important, what the גמרא Gemara said before was, was
that there we will look at a clear context. And there, if
you're... depend on where your hand is on, we will interpret what
you're doing. So even if there's two possible interpretations, we won't always
interpret meaningfully, that's just our bias. But if your hand is on
the... is on the חולין, chullin, then you're doing an act starting
with the חולין, chullin, and that's a language of תמורה. temurah. If
your hand is on the קרבן, korban, you're doing an act starting
with a קרבן, korban, and therefore that is a language of פדיון,
pidyon, not a language of תמורה. temurah. קא משמע לן.
Kama
mashma lan.
So context matters when the word is ambiguous and two meaningful interpretations
are in front of you.
You just reminded me of the רש"י-Grom Rashi one more time.
Well, the רש"י... Rashi... רש"י Rashi says that... that a בעל מום
בבעל מום ba'al mum be'ba'al mum can't do תמורה, temurah, and therefore
we're going to interpret it as פדיון. pidyon. But... the תוספות Tosafot
argues on that, so something we've never heard of. So to me,
so you
would say that it would be... yeah...
it would be תמורה. temurah. Right.
Okay, so then there's not necessarily a favorable interpretation because like they
switched the... or they just weren't addressing... the גמרא Gemara wasn't addressing
that case at all?
No, no, no. תוספות Tosafot has another reason why the גמרא Gemara
thinks that case should have been the... should have been the תמורה
temurah language, but... I mean the פדיון pidyon language, but I didn't
want to get into that. All right, let's take a look now,
the גמרא Gemara continues. אם הקדיש בעל מום יצא לחולין. Im hikdish
ba'al mum yatza lechullin. Now we get into a completely different topic
because the last line of the... of the משנה Mishna is you
clearly were doing פדיון, pidyon, you started with a קרבן korban that
was a בעל מום, ba'al mum, you were doing a פדיון, pidyon,
you transferred it, you used a language of פדיון, pidyon, let's just
say. So no question, you transferred it from the animal with the
בעל מום, ba'al mum, you put it on an unblemished animal. The
last line in the משנה Mishna says וצריך לעשות דמים. vetzarich la'asot
damim. You have to determine its value. You have to... you have
to compute the value, which basically means that even when you're redeeming,
it has to be a fair exchange. You have to transfer it
to another animal that is of equal value. Now, well, but in
the case of the משנה, Mishna, it was an animal. Now what
happens if it was an unequal exchange? You didn't do that. Okay,
so let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says. אם
הקדיש בעל מום יצא לחולין. Im hikdish ba'al mum yatza lechullin. אמר
רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan: יצא לחולין דבר תורה. yatza lechullin devar
Torah. So דאורייתא de'Oraita it becomes desanctified even if it's an unequal
exchange. וצריך לעשות דמים מדבריהם, Vetzarich la'asot damim midivreihem, מדרבנן mi-derabbanan you
have to make up the difference. If you were doing an unequal
exchange, then מדרבנן mi-derabbanan you have to make up the difference. Okay,
it's a little funny what you do with the money. You... I
mean, give it to בדק הבית? Bedek HaBayit? I mean, you're not
going to use it as a קרבן, korban, it's like 20 bucks,
right? You're not going to buy a new קרבן korban with it,
and... your other animals already here. But somehow you go ahead and
you have to give that money to הקדש, hekdesh, you have to
make up the difference. But it really works.
Maybe you get like פדיון השבח? pidyon hashevach?
Maybe. וריש לקיש אמר אף צריך לעשות דמים דבר תורה. V'Reish Lakish
amar af tzarich la'asot damim devar Torah. No, even דאורייתא, de'oraita, even
for the Torah, if you don't make up the difference, then it
does not take effect. Now can you make up the difference after
the fact? That'd be funny, because again, either it was a good
פדיון pidyon or it wasn't. So the way רש"י Rashi says and
what's going to sound clear from the גמרא Gemara is that if
it was an unequal exchange, then the פדיון pidyon did not take
effect. The פדיון pidyon will only take effect if at the time
it was an equal exchange.
במאי עסקינן? Bemai askinan? Now what are we talking about? אי נימא
אונאה, Ei neima ona'ah,
if it was a difference of the amount of אונאה. ona'ah. Now
here we're getting into בבא מציעא Bava Metzia concepts and we're going
to look at this the way we would look at the idea
of a normal sale to from one layperson to another layperson. I
sell you an object. I'm not allowed to overcharge. Now, important concept,
overcharging does not mean that I cannot make a huge profit, okay?
If I go ahead and I, you know, I don't know, come
out with a record or a book or whatever and I charge
however much I want, I can make millions of dollars. That's not
overcharging, okay? Or I can develop a new drug and charge a
thousand dollars a pill. Overcharging is charging more than the market rate,
okay? So that's the concept of אונאה, ona'ah, which raises questions about
things that don't have a, you know, a standard market rate. But
anyway, that is the הלכה halacha of overcharging. I cannot charge more
than the market rate. If I do charge more, first of all
I transgress לא תונו איש את אחיו, lo tonu ish et achiv,
and second of all, now what does that do to affect the
validity of the sale? If it is less than a sixth more
than the standard rate, then we assume it's a very strange הלכה,
halacha, we assume that the sale is good and that you're מוחל.
mochel. It's only, you know, it's only ten, fifteen percent more, you're
מוחל. mochel. If, however, it's exactly a sixth more, then you have
to return, then I have to return to you the overcharge. If
it is more than a sixth more, so if it's exactly a
sixth I return the overcharge, if it is more than a sixth
more, then we say the whole sale, the whole sale is בטל.
batel. מקח טעות, Mekach ta'ut, you never would have wanted to buy
it, the whole sale is בטל. batel. Okay, so, so therefore, how
much did I overcharge הקדש? hekdesh? When there's a question about I
cheated out הקדש, hekdesh, I transferred this קדושה kedusha to something of
lesser value, okay? If it was less than a sixth,
then every, of course it would be good. It would be good
even in a transaction with a layperson.
Like you've even on a value less than a sixth,
with less than a sixth difference of, it's cheaper. Right, if, right,
if it was exactly a sixth lesser value, maybe the question then
is, okay, the transfer worked, but maybe somehow I have to give
הקדש hekdesh back the money. Okay, that would be the, if that's
the question, so let's take a look. Okay, and this is money.
What? And this is just money. Well, that's
what we're going to get to that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
אי נימא אונאה, Ei neima ona'ah, that it was the amount of
אונאה, ona'ah, meaning exactly a sixth, that it was that it was
of lesser value and the question is do you have to give
הקדש hekdesh back the difference like you would to a layperson? So
בהא נימא ריש לקיש אף צריך לעשות דמים דבר תורה, Beha neima
Reish Lakish af tzarich la'asot damim devar Torah, would ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish say there that דאורייתא de'oraita you have to give back the
difference? Why not? והתנן, Vehatnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, as
Michael told us, אלו דברים שאין להם אונאה, Elu devarim she'ein lahem
ona'ah, the following things there are no laws of אונאה, ona'ah, meaning
that overcharging you don't have the consequence of having to pay back
the difference. What are those things? עבדים שטרות וקרקעות, Avadim, shetarot, v'karka'ot,
slaves,
documents, meaning like bills of debt, and קרקע. karka. The reason is
that bills of debt are not of intrinsic value, those are excluded.
Slaves and קרקע karka are just for the examples in the תורה
Torah is about chattel, not about land. Conceptually, by the way, I
should also say that a reason to also think that slaves and
קרקע karka would be different is those are things that are hard
to fix a clear market value on, certainly land. Anyway, והקדשות, v'hekdeshot,
and הקדש hekdesh is also excluded. So there's no הלכה halacha of
paying back a sixth by הקדש. hekdesh. So how could ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish say you have to pay it back? אלא ביטול מקח.
Ela bittul mekach. Okay, so what we're talking about is more than
a sixth. More than a sixth, we're saying that that is such
an unfair exchange that the whole sale was did not go through.
And maybe that would also apply to הקדש. hekdesh. הקדש Hekdesh is
only excluded from the law of a sixth and paying back the
overage, but more than a sixth, maybe that would apply across the
board and that the whole thing would not have been a legitimate
exchange.
Like a package deal.
Yes, so you would think yes. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. ובהא נימא רבי יוחנן צריך לעשות דמים מדבריהם, U'veha
neima Rabbi Yochanan tzarich la'asot damim midivreihem, would there רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan say it's only rabbinic? Shouldn't there everybody agree that it does
not take effect? Why? דאמר רבי ירמיה אקרקעות דחולין רבי יונה אמר
אהקדשות. De'amar Rabbi Yirmiyah akarka'ot dechullin Rabbi Yonah amar ahekdeshot. So רבי
ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah and רבי יונה Rabbi Yonah say in the ובתרוייהו
משמיה דרבי יוחנן. uvetravaihu mishmeih deRabbi Yochanan. So they both have two
traditions from the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. One is that
when it comes to קרקע karka and the other is when it
comes to הקדש, hekdesh, two of the things we excluded from אונאה,
ona'ah, but they both say in
the... They're excluded from the rule of overage, of a sixth, but
they're not excluded from the rule of if it's so disproportionate, the
whole sale doesn't take effect. So here we have one version according
to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that says that when it's הקדש hekdesh
and it's more than a sixth difference, the sale did not take
effect. So how could רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say that it's only
a rabbinic issue when you have this difference of values? Okay, when
it's an unfair exchange. So you got the question? It was an
unfair exchange. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says biblically it's no good, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says rabbinically it's an issue. So the גמרא Gemara
says wait a minute, if it's only a sixth, then everybody should
agree it's not a problem, there's no הלכה halacha of overage by
הקדש, hekdesh, not a biblical problem. If it's more than a sixth,
then even רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan should say that it doesn't take
effect because here he's quoted as saying it doesn't take effect if
it's more than a sixth. So the גמרא Gemara says let's take
a look.
The גמרא Gemara says לעולם, le'olam, where am I? אמרי אונאה אין
להם ביטול מקח יש להם. amri ona'ah ein lahem bitul mekach yeish
lahem. לעולם ביטול מקח. le'olam bitul mekach. Fine. The debate of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is does it actually,
does
the whole thing nullify? ואיפוך, ve'eiphach, reverse the names. ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says it's only rabbinic and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it's
biblical because here we have a tradition of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
that says that when it's more than a sixth, the whole thing
is negated. So the גמרא Gemara says ומי מצית אמרת איפוך? umi
matzis amart eiphach? Can you really reverse it? הני למאן דאמר הקדש
וכל שכן קרקעות. hani l'man d'amar hekdesh ve'chol shekein karka'os. That's good
according to the first opinion, I mean the opinion of רבי יונה
Rabbi Yona that says that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say when
it comes to הקדש, hekdesh, parenthetically and certainly by land, why certainly
is based on the דרשות, drashos, I don't want to go into
it, anyway by הקדש hekdesh that it really is בטל batel when
it's more than a sixth. אלא למאן דאמר קרקעות, ella l'man d'amar
karka'os, but according to רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya who only said רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said by land that it would be nullified, אבל
הקדשות אין להם ביטול מקח, aval hekdeshos ein lahem bitul mekach, according
to him even רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say, or רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan would say that when it comes to הקדש, hekdesh, there
is no idea of nullified. Got it? Meaning the גמרא Gemara says
that the הלכה halacha is there's no law of overage. Then there
are versions in which maybe רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say there
is a nullified מקח mekach when it's too much, according to one
version by הקדש, hekdesh, another version קרקע. karka. So according to the
version הקדש, hekdesh, the גמרא Gemara says reverse the people because obviously
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying that it would be בטל. batel.
But says fine, that's according to him, but according to the guy
that says that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan only said that it's בטל
batel by land, but by הקדש hekdesh it's never nullified, it doesn't
work to reverse it. So the גמרא Gemara says אבל הקדשות
אין להם ביטול מקח היכי אפיך להו? aval hekdeshos ein lahem bitul
mekach heichi aphich lehu? How could you reverse it? So the גמרא
Gemara says fine, לא אמר רבי ירמיה לא תיפוך. la amar Rabbi
Yirmiya lo teiphach. Fine, according to רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya you wouldn't
reverse it. Okay, so basically right we have two versions whether רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say that by הקדש hekdesh the sale is
בטל batel when it's too much, more than a sixth. So according
to the version that he would say it was בטל, batel, then
we reverse the names of the debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it's biblical
that it doesn't work and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says rabbinic. According
to the version that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan never said that by
הקדש, hekdesh, even by הקדש hekdesh it's not בטל, batel, then it's
only ריש לקיש Reish Lakish who would say that it is בטל,
batel, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would not say it is בטל. batel.
But however it lines up, רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, the basic interpretation we're giving to the debate is your exchange
was uneven, it was more than a sixth difference from the price,
and therefore will it be, will it take effect that redemption? So
according to at least one opinion no, although הקדש hekdesh is excluded
from אונאה, ona'ah, when it's too big of a difference, it does
not take effect. That is how, whether it's רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, that's how we're reading it. Now the גמרא
Gemara says
it's nothing essentially that they do.
Well, right, you tried like you tried to do a sale, but
it was an unfair sale, so you have to try to do
it again. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara now says, and you see
Michael I was waiting for you to ask this, how could we
be having this whole conversation? We have a famous teaching of שמואל
Shmuel that says that when you do a redemption, even if it
is grossly unequal, it still takes effect. You might not be allowed
to do it, but it still takes effect. So let's take a
look. נימא בדישמואל קמיפלגי? neima b'diShmuel kamifligi? It sounds like maybe they're
debating שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר שמואל, de'amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel says, הקדש שוה
מנה שחיללו שוה פרוטה, hekdesh shaveh maneh shechillalo shaveh perutah, you've got
הקדש hekdesh worth a hundred מנה, maneh, like a hundred thousand dollars,
and you transfer it to a פרוטה, perutah, מחולל, mechulal, it works
בדיעבד. bedi'avad. You're not allowed to do it, okay, you're cheating out
הקדש, hekdesh, but it works. And here we're saying that they're debating
whether it even works post facto. So doesn't it sound like, now
some switch the gears here, רבי יונה Rabbi Yona and רבי ירמיה
Rabbi Yirmiya to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
Okay, but whoever the two positions are, רבי יונה לית ליה דשמואל,
Rabbi Yona leis lei d'Shmuel, רבי ירמיה אית ליה דשמואל. Rabbi Yirmiya
is lei d'Shmuel. רבי יונה Rabbi Yona or according to the other
version ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, whatever it is, רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
the one that says that it does take effect holds like שמואל,
Shmuel, and רבי ירמיה, Rabbi Yirmiya, again those were the two versions
of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, holds,
excuse me, the one that says that it does not take effect
rejects שמואל, Shmuel, and the one that says that it does take
effect holds like שמואל. Shmuel. So we're having a debate now between
two versions of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan or רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish whether it takes effect or not when
it's
too... No, the גמרא Gemara says
no,
בין למר בין למר, bein lemar bein lemar, whether according to either
opinion again of רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan and ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish,
which is a different גרסא girsa than the one we have here,
אית ליה דשמואל, is leh deShmuel, they really hold like שמואל. Shmuel.
רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan סבר savar כי אמר שמואל ki amar Shmuel
בדיעבד b'diavad אבל aval לכתחילה l'chatchila לא. lo. According to the one
that says that it does not take effect, he would say okay,
when did שמואל Shmuel say it? He only said it post facto,
but לכתחילה l'chatchila you're not supposed to do it, לא אמר. lo
amar. ורבי ירמיה veReb Yirmiyah סבר savar and רבי ירמיה Reb Yirmiyah
would hold אפילו afilu לכתחילה, l'chatchila, even לכתחילה. l'chatchila. Now what does
this mean? Normally when the גמרא Gemara says about שמואל Shmuel לכתחילה
l'chatchila and בדיעבד, b'diavad, it means exactly what the terms לכתחילה l'chatchila
בדיעבד b'diavad usually mean. שמואל Shmuel only said you can do it
post if post facto it worked, never said you're supposed to transfer
a hundred thousand dollars onto a penny. But that doesn't work here
because the גמרא Gemara can't say oh, they're only debating whether you're
allowed to do this לכתחילה l'chatchila or not, because it was very
clear that the way the גמרא Gemara at least framed the debate
of רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was based
on the question of ביטול מקח bitul mekach and whether the whole
thing you know went through even post facto. Maybe post facto it
didn't work at all. So how could you say it's based on
a לכתחילה l'chatchila question? So רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both and
תוספות Tosafot admittedly does a you know a very sort of forced
re-read of the phrase לכתחילה l'chatchila and says לכתחילה l'chatchila doesn't mean
whether you're allowed to do it. Okay, what לכתחילה l'chatchila means, let
me just sort of double check before I say this again.
Oh right, okay. That when it says לכתחילה l'chatchila it works, לכתחילה
l'chatchila doesn't mean that you that you're allowed to do it. Actually
לכתחילה l'chatchila means that that's what you were trying to do. If
you were willfully, consciously trying to do an uneven exchange, okay you
think that makes it worse, but no, then you are trying then
you know you're not trying if you're if you're trying if you
know what you're doing then it takes effect. That's שמואל'ס Shmuel's case.
You knew what you were doing, a hundred thousand dollars and a
penny, you knew exactly what you were doing, an uneven exchange. If
that's how you want to operate, fine, it takes effect. But if
you're not aware of that, meaning as opposed to בדיעבד, b'diavad, בדיעבד
b'diavad means like it was not what you were trying to do.
Okay, it's a very you know forced read of the phrase לכתחילה
l'chatchila בדיעבד, b'diavad, but if it wasn't what you were trying to
do, in your mind you were trying to do a fair exchange
and actually it wound up being uneven, in that case it wasn't
what you intended. That was so different from what you intended that
therefore it does not take effect. So that's how we are reframing
according to רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot the debate.
If you willfully, what you were trying to intend.
Yeah, one bit of money, another animal, I get somebody to come
ahead and do an assessment and figure out exactly how much this
animal's worth, this car, this car, let's exchange, I thought it was
fair, right? And then oh no actually this one is sickly and
this one has a broken leg or whatever it was, okay, but
it wasn't what I was intending. So according to that it actually
makes sense because if you think about it, the whole idea that
we apply the laws of ביטול מקח bitul mekach to הקדש hekdesh
is very strange, right? It's not like there's another side. It's like
you and the animals. And it's not only that, if it's a
case of בדק הבית, bedek habayit, which is actually שמואל'ס Shmuel's case
interestingly, then it really is another side. They own it and your
act of redemption could be seen as a type of an act
of purchase. But if it's the case of a קרבן, korban, it's
not so much that הקדש hekdesh owns it, it's just you're transferring
the קדושה. kedusha. So why should the difference of values be treated
like a basically like a you know like a מקח טעות, mekach
taut, like a false sale? It wasn't a sale, I'm transferring values.
So the way the גמרא Gemara now reframes it is that it's
not really about the laws of ביטול מקח, bitul mekach, it's really
a question about being different from what you intended. Okay, if you
knew what you were doing and you were doing an uneven exchange,
fine, you know what you're doing, it takes effect. You're not supposed
to do it, but it takes effect. If you actually are trying
to do an even exchange, it doesn't take effect, not because so
much it's ביטול מקח, bitul mekach, but more because by analogy to
ביטול מקח bitul mekach it is so off base and you were
trying to do fair and it was so unfair that therefore that's
why it does not take effect because that was so different from
what you were trying to do.
Then you first have to make up the difference though. What? You
still have to make up the difference?
Well then you might have right, according to well according to ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish who interprets the whole thing about בדיעבד, b'diavad, he
might he wouldn't say make up the difference, he'd say do it
again. According to רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan that says it takes effect,
then it would even in that case it would take effect and
yes, pay the difference. Okay, so let's now continue. The גמרא Gemara
says like this, ואיבעית אימא ve'iba'it eima so,
ואיבעית אימא ve'iba'it eima if you want I could say לעולם לא
תיפוך. le'olam lo teiphach. Don't reverse any of the names, okay, keep
it רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish even if
רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan says ביטול מקח bitul mekach by more than
a סלע. sela. Okay, so then what are they debating? דקשיא לך
מתניתין אלו
דברים הקדשות, De-kachashya lecha matnitin elo devarim hekdeshos, you were bothered by
the משנה Mishnah about these are the things and הקדשות כדרב חסדא
hekdeshos kid'Rav Chisda that רב חסדא Rav Chisda says that רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan would say in a case of הקדש hekdesh it would
be בטל. battel. So how could רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say it's
only a rabbinic problem?
So דאמר רב חסדא, d'amar Rav Chisda, כדרב חסדא, kid'Rav Chisda, I'm
sorry, like רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. דאמר רב חסדא אין להם אונאה,
D'amar Rav Chisda ein lahem ona'ah, because רב חסדא Rav Chisda says
אין להם אונאה. ein lahem ona'ah. What does it mean that הקדש
hekdesh doesn't have אונאה? ona'ah? It means אינם בתורת אונאה דאפילו בפחות
מכדי אונאה חוזר. einam b'toras ona'ah d'afillu b'pachos mik'dei ona'ah chozer. It
means the exact opposite. Not that there's no laws of אונאה ona'ah
by הקדש, hekdesh, but that there's always אונאה ona'ah by הקדש. hekdesh.
Right? We understood what does it mean הקדש hekdesh has no אונאה?
ona'ah? There's never a problem. And then that led us to an
idea of what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said ביטול מקח bittul mekach
and we had to reverse names.
This interpretation of רב חסדא Rav Chisda that says that when it
comes to הקדש, hekdesh, אין להם אונאה ein lahem ona'ah means even
for a penny off, there's always a problem of אונאה. ona'ah. You
always have to return the money. And now the debate of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is not whether it
takes effect when you do a gross overcharge, more than a sixth.
Now the debate is when you do a minor overcharge. The difference
was only a few dollars. Okay, in that case רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says no problem, there's no אונאה ona'ah by הקדש, hekdesh, it
works. Make up the difference דרבנן. d'rabbanan. And ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says no, you always have to make up the difference דאורייתא d'oraisa
because הקדש hekdesh there are no limits to אונאה. ona'ah. You always
have to return it even if it's only a slight overcharge. But
it would take effect. But it would take effect. So now there
are, let's just take a step back, two different interpretations of the
debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. One
is that your exchange was grossly uneven. According to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, let's just go by the first version, not the איפכא ipcha
version. According to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, it takes effect because there's
no אונאה ona'ah by הקדש. hekdesh. It's שמואל Shmuel's הלכה, halacha, בדיעבד
b'diavad it takes effect even if it's uneven, but rabbinically pay the
difference. That's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says no, it doesn't even take effect. What about שמואל? Shmuel? Well,
when you're trying to do, when you're intentionally doing an unequal exchange
it takes effect. When you're trying to do an equal exchange, it
doesn't. Do it again. That's because it was so grossly unfair and
you were trying to do equal. That's one version. It was grossly
unfair, did it take effect or not? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
it takes effect, pay the difference. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says doesn't
take effect. The other version is it was not grossly unfair, it
was only off by a very little. Okay, so there רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says fine, it was off by a little, takes effect,
there's no אונאה ona'ah by הקדש, hekdesh, just pay the difference. And
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says yes, it takes effect, but you have
to pay the difference דאורייתא d'oraisa because by הקדש hekdesh there's always
אונאה. ona'ah. And therefore biblically you have to pay the difference. How
does that work with שמואל? Shmuel? Again, I don't know. Maybe שמואל
Shmuel is different. שמואל Shmuel's a case where you're intentionally doing it
unfair. If you're trying to be fair, these are the rules that
apply.
So it's an exchange of animals, basically the
same, like an animal for an animal, this ox for that ox,
you know, רובא ברובא, rubas b'rubas, something like that. Right. Very.
So that's why, yes, so that's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says.
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says I'm sorry, when you deal with הקדש
hekdesh you gotta be super careful.
You know, but in the, but that means, but according to everybody,
according to at least one of these versions, you still, you know,
do the difference. Right.
Exactly. To the penny, you're off like three cents and,
I don't know if they would actually determine, you know, animals, you
know, that precisely. I don't know. Okay, but there still could be
ways that they could be off even if it was not that
precise pricing.
Okay, so there'd be a markas.
Exactly, there's a market value
and that they have more valuable types of animals.
Exactly. Okay, so let's finish up this
פרק. perek. אמר עולא לא אמרו אלא בשומא בתרי. Amar Ulla lo
amru ela b'shumai b'trei. Only this applies only if the value was
assessed with two people. Meaning how do you know your valuation was
off? Okay, so basically שמואל Shmuel imagines that you got two people
to come and assess it. That's what happened in the case. Okay,
thank you, I'm going to get back to that. שמואל Shmuel assumes
that you get two people to come to assess it, you did
an exchange, and then afterwards a more expert assessment told you no,
no, no, you were off. And therefore according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish you have to pay the difference,
question דאורייתא, d'oraisa, דרבנן, d'rabbanan, and so on. Now of course you
could have imagined cases you didn't even bother with an assessment. But
שמואל, Shmuel, and that's why you were off. But שמואל Shmuel's imagining
you got an assessment but it actually was a not valid one.
It was two and then it gets overridden and then is the
issue of paying the difference.
אבל בשומא בתלתא, Aval b'shumai b'tlasa, if you actually do a שומא
shuma with three, with a בית דין, beis din, אף על גב
דאתי במאה, af al gav d'asi b'me'ah, even if afterwards a hundred
come and say you made a difference, once a בית דין beis
din determined the assessment, that's the fixed value. לא הדר, Lo hadar,
it does not go back and either it's not a ביטול מקח
bittul mekach or you don't have to pay the difference. איני, Aini,
is that true? ואמר רב ספרא היכא דאמר מאה כתרי ותרי כמאה,
V'amar Rav Safra heicha d'amar me'ah k'trei u'trei k'me'ah, when do we
say a hundred is like two and two is like a hundred,
meaning when do we say that they're equivalent? לעניין עדות, L'inyan eidus,
when it comes to testimony. There there's a formal rule that once
you have two, they're as good as a hundred witnesses. אבל לעניין
אומדנא, Aval l'inyan umdana, but when it goes to assessing values, בתר
דעות אזלינן, basar de'os azlinan,
there's no formalism, the more... More opinions the better. So if you
have a hundred experts versus three experts, there’s no formalism of a
בית דין. Beis din. Okay, you go by the majority of experts.
The majority so therefore the later assessment would override the earlier one
and you should be considered off and you would have to pay
the difference even though it was unintentional and remember we said the
whole scenario here was you were trying to be fair but nevertheless
we should reassess and you should have to pay the difference.
So you don’t have to do another assessment though.
No you don’t have to but it happened.
Okay so the גמרא Gemara said ותו תלתא ותלתא לא אזלינן בתר
בתרא? v'tu tlasa v'tlasa lo azlinan basar basra? בתר בתרא? Basar basra?
דיד הקדש? D'yad hekdesh? It even if it was three and three
would we not go by the second one why not דיד הקדש
על העליונה? d'yad hekdesh al elyonah? We’ll always go to the favor
of הקדש hekdesh so therefore we’ll always go by the latter one
certainly if it’s equivalent certainly if it’s better and therefore you should
have to pay the difference so why do we allow you to
stick by the first by the first assessment? So the גמרא Gemara
says no קסבר עולא צריך לעשות תמים מדבריהן kasavar Ulla tzarich la'asos
tamim midivrei hen and he holds like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that
paying the difference is only rabbinic and since it’s only rabbinic so
therefore וכל דרבנן אקילו בה רבנן v'chol d'rabbanan akilu bah rabbanan since
it’s only rabbinic they went easy by you and they said if
you got a formal assessment of three we’re not going to reassess
even though you might be הלכתית halachically we’re entitled to but we’re
not going to because we want to make life a little easier
this whole thing is only rabbinic. So just first of all to
address Michael’s point and then to sum up Michael said one minute
I thought there’s a הלכה halacha that you need a hundred I
mean not a hundred you need ten for הקדש. hekdesh. So תוספות
Tosafos asked that question and תוספות Tosafos basically says that it’s a
difference whether the whether the גזבר gizbar the treasurer is redeeming it
or you the בעל הבית ba'al habayis is redeeming it. Right this
goes back to I think the question before when you’re the בעל
הבית ba'al habayis who’s doing it you have a lot of latitude
you put the הקדש hekdesh you can transfer the הקדש hekdesh it’s
true you have to add a חומש chomesh which by the way
interestingly is ignored here in this גמרא Gemara because here it sounds
like equivalent there’s another הלכה halacha about a חומש chomesh but anyway
you’re the בעל הבית ba'al habayis you’re able to do it yourself
and the whole issue of assessment is like okay what happens if
it wound up being unfair making up the difference and so on.
The הלכה halacha that you need a ten to do it is
when actually it’s being done through an act of the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash the גזבר gizbar has it because it’s temple treasury not
a קרבן korban and it’s been handed over to the גזבר gizbar
and now he is going and he is selling it to other
people so that is a more formal thing it also provides oversight
although the גמרא Gemara learns it out from a פסוק pasuk right
and there it’s actually הקדש hekdesh is selling it and there you
do the assessment of ten.
So to sum up and that you don’t overturn.
That you would not overturn.
It’s like another hundred
presumably right that’s a good point but presumably. So now again to
to restate שמואל Shmuel has a statement which the גמרא Gemara loves
quoting והיא דהקדש כשווה v'hi d'hikdish k'shva this גמרא Gemara is like
a should be a shock because normally we always know about שמואל
Shmuel שמואל Shmuel says that even if it’s a hundred thousand dollars
to a penny it works but the גמרא Gemara here seems to
qualify that that again the way רש"י Rashi תוספות Tosafos read it
it wasn’t so clear that’s what the גמרא Gemara was saying but
that’s the way רש"י Rashi תוספות Tosafos read it that is when
you are knowingly doing an unfair exchange you’re not supposed to but
you know you have a certain but you created the הקדש hekdesh
you have that latitude it does take effect even though you wound
up cheating out הקדש hekdesh that’s if it’s knowing but if you’re
trying to do a fair exchange then there’s a הלכה halacha that
if you’re off you have to make up the difference. So if
you’re grossly off
then according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish it even the whole thing
isn’t doesn’t even take effect. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan takes effect make
up the difference. If you’re only off by a little bit so
there too as well there is a similar way of framing the
debate that they both agree that if it’s only off by a
little bit make up the difference but רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
rabbinic ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says biblical. The רמב"ם Rambam rules by
all of this rabbinic that you make up the difference it always
takes effect you make up the difference and that’s only a rabbinic
rule. Okay now we finish up this פרק. perek.
It’s only when you’re undercharged
when
you have cheated הקדש hekdesh right when your second animal is less
yeah no problem okay you want to give more to הקדש hekdesh
be my guest. הרי זו תחת עולה תחת חטאת לא אמר כלום.
Harei zo tachas olah tachas chatas lo amar klum.
Now here we are finally saying what was always assumed by תמורה
Temurah it’s so funny this comes way at the end if you
just say generically this animal is instead of a חטאת chatas instead
of an עולה olah it’s meaningless. תמורה Temurah is when you are
connecting it to a very specific animal that’s when the one you
are sort of trying to dethrone that’s what’s problematic about it and
that’s also what allows it to become קדוש kadosh because the קדושה
kedusha of the existing animal you know sort of gets extended to
it but if you just do a generic this is an exchange
of a חטאת chatas that does not work. If you said however
לא אמר כלום lo amar klum תחת חטאת זו tachas chatas zo
instead of this חטאת chatas תחת עולה זו tachas olah zo this
עולה olah תחת חטאת ותחת עולה שיש לי בבית tachas chatas v'tachas
olah sheyesh li babayis
or you say the עולה olah and the חטאת chatas that I
have in my house והיו לו v'hayu lo you have them so
they don’t have to be in front of you that’s important they
don’t have to be in front of you but they have to
be specific ones that you are designate that you are relating to.
In those cases דבריו קיימים d'varav kayamim that that works. Again works
bad but it’s an act of תמורה Temurah you’re trying to dethrone
a specific קרבן korban and because it connects to a specific קרבן
korban it becomes קדוש. kadosh. אמר על בהמה טמאה או בעלת מום
הרי אלו עולה Amar al behemah tmeiah o ba'alas mum harei elu
olah
now... In a total different shift, okay, but connects to things from
a few פרקים prakim ago, you say on a non-kosher animal, a
camel, this is an עולה, olah, or an animal with a מום,
mum, this is an עולה, olah, לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum,
you didn't say anything. Now that's interesting. We normally assume that if
you're מקדיש makdish a בעל מום, ba'al mum, it gets קדושת דמים.
kedushas damim. But the גמרא Gemara actually says it depends, this משנה,
Mishnah, how you phrase it. If you say it's an עולה, olah,
well a בעל מום ba'al mum can't be an עולה, olah, so
it's actually meaningless. הרי אלו לעולה, Harei elu l'olah,
these should be for an עולה, olah, that means they should go
towards an עולה, olah, ימכרו ויביא בדמיהם עולה. yimachru v'yavi bidmeihem olah.
Then you go ahead and you sell them and you use the
proceeds for an עולה. olah. So here it's interesting, if you say
by בעל מום ba'al mum directly it's an עולה, olah, it does
not get קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, it might have been like saying
it by a car and a camel and it's meaningless, okay? Only
if you say for an עולה olah does it mean that it
gets value קדושה kedushah and the money goes for an עולה. olah.
Okay, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, מתניתין דלא כרבי מאיר. masnisin d'lo
k'Rabbi Meir. Our משנה Mishnah is not like
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. דרבי מאיר, D'Rabbi Meir, הא אין אדם מוציא
דבריו לבטלה. ha ein adam motzi devarav l'vatalah. According to רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, you don't say things for naught and we will interpret
your words in a meaningful way. Now what does that mean? So
תוספות Tosafos says it could mean for the first statement, if you
said הרי זו תחת עולה, harei zo tachas olah, that we interpret
it to mean תחת עולה זו tachas olah zo and turn it
into an act of תמורה. temurah. Okay, but that's a little bit
of an extreme and תוספות Tosafos much more favors that this statement
was going on the second half of the משנה, Mishnah, that when
you just said הרי זו עולה, harei zo olah, even if it
was on your camel or on your בעל מום, ba'al mum, we'll
interpret it to be לעולה. l'olah. Okay, we won't say that you
didn't sanctify it at all, but in this context it's not as
big a jump to say what you mean is the proceeds for
an עולה olah rather than saying an עולה olah itself.
Did you say the first statement as פדיון?
pidyon? No, because that would also, the first statement was generic, it
wasn't even a specific עולה olah in front of you.
Right, so why would you assume the worst?
Well, oh, you mean because of the language of תחת. tachas. Well,
then that goes back to the whole previous discussion about what תחת
tachas means. But anyway, okay, now
the גמרא Gemara goes on, הרי אלו לעולה ימכרו ויביא בדמיהם עולה.
harei elu l'olah yimachru v'yavi bidmeihem olah. טעמא דבהמה טמאה בעלת מום
דלא חזין לא בעיין מומא. Ta'ama d'behemah teme'ah ba'alas mum d'lo chazyan
lo ba'in muma. That's true, with a non-kosher animal or it's got
a blemish, since they're not fit they don't need a מום, mum,
I mean you want to have a מום, mum, but okay, but
the camel doesn't need a מום, mum, you can redeem it without
it, right? It's like sanctifying a car, as I said, doesn't need
a מום. mum. אבל מקדיש נקבה לאשם עולה לעולה בעיין מומא. Aval
makdish nekeivah l'asham, olah, l'olah, ba'in muma. But presumably if it wasn't
as radical as that, if it was a female that you were
doing for an עולה olah or female you were doing for an
אשם, asham, in that type of a case it would need a
blemish and this is the question we had before. Does the wrong
gender, is it like a מום? mum? Or another way of saying
it, not like is it like a מום, mum, but is it
like a camel? Is it so inappropriate that it was only קדושת
דמים? kedushas damim? And here it's saying that implicitly, since the משנה
Mishnah didn't address it, it does need a blemish, it is not
considered radically different. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav, מתניתין דלא כרבי שמעון, masnisin d'lo k'Rabbi Shimon, therefore it would
not be like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, דתנן, d'tanan, רבי שמעון אומר,
Rabbi Shimon omer, תימכר שלא במום. timacher shelo b'mum. These things do
not require a מום. mum. Our משנה Mishnah somehow the גמרא Gemara
is assuming, suggests that they would, only the case of a camel
and a בעל מום ba'al mum would be different, but a wrong
gender would still require a מום. mum. הדרן לך תשעה מראין. Hadran
lach tish'at mar'in.